<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peace of enmity A sermon preached in Paules Church the 12 day of February, in the yeere of our Lord God, 1639. By Augustine Hill, rector of Dengey in the county of Essex.</title>
            <author>Hill, Augustine, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104107</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839846</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839846</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4303</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03346)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4303)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1489:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peace of enmity A sermon preached in Paules Church the 12 day of February, in the yeere of our Lord God, 1639. By Augustine Hill, rector of Dengey in the county of Essex.</title>
                  <author>Hill, Augustine, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 24, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. P[urslowe] for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at his shop, at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Genesis III, 15.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4303:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4303:1"/>
            <p>THE PEACE OF ENMITY.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in PAULES Church the 12 day of <hi>February,</hi> in the yeere of our Lord God, 1639.</p>
            <p>BY AUGUSTINE HILL, Rector of <hi>Dengey</hi> in the County of ESSEX.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>AUG.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Pacem habete cum hominibus, Bellum cum Diabolo, vitiis, vanitatibus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by E. P. for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the South Entrance of the Royall Exchange. 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4303:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4303:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE HENRY GARWAY, Lord Maior of the City Of LONDON; And to the Right Worſhipfull The ALDERMEN His BRETHREN:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Lord-ſhips favourable acceptance of my weak endeavours puts life into them, which were even before their birth dead, in mine owne opinion of them, and had dyed as ſoone as they were borne, but that you was pleaſed to breathe upon them, ſo that having from you received a publike life, they humbly beg of your Lordſhip to foſter them, in this hard cenſorious age. Your encouragements came to me, as Gods mercy came to Adam, and us in him in my text, in the needfull time of trouble, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are more gratefull to me, and with more grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb facs="tcp:4303:3"/>
ought to bee, and are received. God knowes beſt which way to bring us to himſelfe, and if our Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage was ſweet, we ſhold forget our Countrey, yet where God ſends us comforts, not to kiſſe that hand, by which we receive them, is wretched unthankfulneſse. My poore Sermon, enriched by your Honours acceptance, flyes into your boſome for ſhelter, and may the comforts exhibited therein, remaine there, and in the hearts of all yours, and of all the pillars of this governement, whereof you are principall. It is publiſhed as neere as I could, <hi>totidem verbis,</hi> as it was preached. I feared to adde any thing to it, leſt that which was put to, might be diſpleaſing to your Lordſhip, and ſo diſcarded of your protection, or to leave out any thing, leſt ſome part of it (though never ſo meane) might have bin bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall to one or other, and ſo an iniury done in the loſſe of it. It hath a great diſadvantage, in that what lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle life there was in the delivery, is wholy loſt, unleſſe quickned by the Fancy and apprehenſion of the reader, whoſe eare might reliſh that which the eye will perhaps diſtaſte, and for my ſelfe, though preaching bee my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull burden, yet the preſſe is a preſſure more then ordinary to me, being no whit acquainted that way, nor having friends and acquaintance to direct mee in it. But I beſeech you to cover all my weakeneſses with your moſt favourable conſtruction, and not onely to cover them your ſelfe, but to ſhelter them from the ſtormes of cenſure, which are likely to light on them. The Lord continue and encreaſe unto you the bleſſings of his right hand and of his left, and to thoſe that are your right hand and right eye, in the Governement of this anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:4303:3"/>
corporation, the right Worſpipfull, the Aldermen your Brethren, that you and they may ſee clearely into, and ſee ſtrongly executed thoſe things which belong to the ſafety and welfare of this renowned body, and that they, whoſe lips preſerve knowledge, may ſtill have a cheerefull portion of meat in due ſeaſon. It is the Crowne of your honour and eſtates, and your poore Oratour will pray that it may ever flouriſh, and that the Oyle may abound in your cruſes, and multiply in the effuſion of it, as is the deſire of him that is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, ready to be commanded AUGUSTINE HILL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4303:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4303:4"/>
            <head>THE PEACE OF ENMITY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 3.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I will put enmity betweene thee and the woman, and betweene thy ſeed and her ſeed, he ſhall breake thy head, and thou ſhalt bruſe his heele.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen God had made the great world, hee made man the little world, as an abſtract of the creation, <hi>&amp; Epilogus operum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> a concluſion of all his workes, placed him in paradiſe, who was a Paradiſe in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; his ſoule as rich as that ſoile, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, becauſe cloathed with innocency, inſtead of a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Sin it was that opened the eyes of his body, and ſhut the eyes of his mind, cloathed his outward and ſtript his inward man: <hi>hinc illae lachrymae,</hi> hence are the teares of us his poſterity. The ſumme is that of Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: God made man righteous, but he hath ſought out many inventions, and in ſeeking his inventions, hee found a way to loſe himſelfe, and all of us. But God had mercy on him, and not on him onely, but on us alſo, and by a gracious promiſe of his owne ſonne in my text, reſtores him. Mortality ſeazeth upon Adam, everlaſting death had ſtretched out her hand to have ſmitten him (as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> did againſt the Prophet) but God withered it. Iuſtice cries give, give, and ſets open her devouring
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4303:5"/>
throat to ſwallow him, but the Lord ſtops her mouth with a morſell from Heaven. The ſubſtance of my text is Gods wonderfull mercy in ſinfull Adams reſtauration, brought in by a gracious Parentheſis, in the midſt of Gods juſtice, and mans neceſſity, in the very pinch of extremity, like a ſhowre of raine in the time of draught, or <hi>tanquam flos roſarum in diebus hybernis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iſidore.</note>The weight and moment of the matter, requires your at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: it's <hi>Oceanus Theologiae,</hi> a maine Ocean of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, it is <hi>omnis latitudo Scripturarum,</hi> the whole breadth of Scripture, our fore-fathers Goſpel, and the ſeminary of ours. On this, the eyes of all primitive believers were fixed, and by faith in this promiſe were ſaved. 'Tis the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Chriſtian Faith, the ſecret of Chriſtian hope, the inducement of Chriſtian love, and therefore ought to bee thrice welcome to us Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The juſt Judge of all things, commonly ordinates the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to the offence, he that is the firſt in ſinning, muſt be the firſt in ſuffering, Adam, the laſt in the tranſgreſſion, muſt be the laſt in execution. The <hi>Anathema</hi> firſt takes hold on the ſerpent,<note place="margin">Bernard. Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>Diabolum ſerpentem,</hi> or <hi>Diabolum per ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> the divell by the ſerpent, ſpeaking through that cane and trunke, like a Ieſuite through an image, whoſe male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, as it is divided into two verſes, ſo it hath divided the mindes of men into two opinions, ſome reſtrayning it to the ſpirituall ſerpent the Divell, others conjoyning the terrene ſerpent, as a ſharer of the puniſhment, which is moſt conſonant to divine Iuſtice, which puniſheth the act done, and ſuffereth not the meanes by which it is done, to goe ſcot-free: as an affectionate father, having his only ſon mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, cauſeth not only the murtherer himſelfe to ſuffer condigne puniſhment, but expreſſeth his indignation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that weapon, by which that bloody fact was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> In the former verſe God wrackes the inſtrument, in this he ruines the author of rebellion. <hi>I will put enmity between thee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4303:5"/>My text is, like the times, litigious, it thunders out warres, and rumors of warres, ſeditions, tumults, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctations, enmity. We may name it as Iſaack did the firſt well he digged, <hi>Eſek</hi> contention, or his ſecond well,<note place="margin">Gen. 16, 20, 21</note> 
               <hi>Sitnah</hi> hatred: contention, and hatred are in it, open violence and ſecret circumvention: God himſelfe the breeder of this contention, the occaſioner of this quarrel 'tis <hi>vox Dei</hi> the voice of God and not of man, who here is both a Prophet, and a Preacher of enmity, <hi>I will put Enmity;</hi> and therefore it is not evill, for God himſelfe, who is goodneſſe it ſelfe, is author of it: It is not caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or contingent, as the Philiſtines were halfe perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of their plague of Emerodes, a chance had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to them: but a predeſtinate, previſed decree,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 6.</note> a ſetled enmity, <hi>I will put,</hi> tis not a ſlender and triviall diſcord, but enmity it ſelf in the abſtract; tis not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt in regard of the adverſe parties, the Serpent, and the woman, once at a falſe amity, now God puts a true enmity betwixt them; which was not onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall, bounded to themſelves alone, but derived to their poſterities, <hi>perpetuum certamen,</hi> an everlaſting conflict betweene them, and their ſeedes for ever: nor is the iſſue uncomfortable, for the victory is already determined for the woman, and her ſeed: <hi>he ſhall breake,</hi> &amp;c. Now whereas the Septuagint render it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervabit te,</hi> it ſhould rather be, as a Critick obſerves, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>conteret;</hi> or elſe it is too ſhort, and though the Originall be equall in both, yet Divines have generally noted an inequality, <hi>multo gravius accipies damnum quàm offeres.</hi> He ſhall breake thy head,<note place="margin">Tremell.</note> and thou ſhalt (but) bruiſe his heele.</p>
            <p>So that my text is, <hi>Caſtrorum acies bene ordinata,</hi> an army well marſhalled where every one keepes his place and ranke.</p>
            <p>Firſt, here is the prime <hi>agent,</hi> and heavenly diſpoſer, <hi>I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, his active power, determination or conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution it ſelfe, <hi>will put.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4303:6"/>Thirdly, the Inſtrument, or meanes uſed to effect it, <hi>enmity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly the ſubjects of this contrariety, <hi>the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and the woman,</hi> his ſeed and her ſeed, oppoſite <hi>ex Diametro</hi> one to the other.</p>
            <p>Fiftly the effects. <hi>He ſhall breake thy head, and thou ſhalt &amp;c.</hi> or in military tearmes, we have,</p>
            <p>Firſt the moover of this quarrell, divine goodneſſe, juſtice, and providence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the meaſure of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>enmity,</hi> not onely <hi>ſimultas,</hi> a ſecret ſpleene, but open manifeſt malice, and deteſtation, joyned with a deſire to do hurt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly the Antagoniſts or Combatants; The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and the woman, and their innumerable armies.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Succeſſe of the Combat, the conflict is fierce, there are hurts on both ſides; but the conqueſt is glorious: <hi>He ſhall breake thy head,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the one Champion you may ſee valour, and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; valour in that he aymes, and ſtrikes at the head: victory in that he breakes the head. In the other, Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe and Weakeneſſe: Malice joyned with power reſtreyned, and diſabled to performe his miſchievous intents: In that he can but bruiſe, though he deſires to doe more, and that but the heele, though he deſires to goe farther: Thou ſhalt but bruiſe, his fleſh is impene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable; and but his heele, his body is impregnable.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.24.</note>Yet this is but the casket, there is a rich jewell within, for I muſt uſe the Apoſtle his phraſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Theſe things are an Allegory, there is a ſweet kernell ſhut up under this ſhell of words? And this particle <hi>he,</hi> or <hi>it</hi> hath a double portion among the reſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a moſt faire, and rich Margarite: Chriſt himſelfe, a precious treaſure hid here in this field of enmity, and he whom the heaven of heavens cannot containe, is couched in this ſmall continent, The ſeed of the woman, by whom the head of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4303:6"/>
muſt be broken, the Sonne of God, in whom all the nations of the earth muſt be bleſſed. I am ſure, full of grace and truth are theſe wordes, in God the Father, ſo fully, freely, and fitly promiſing to ſend his owne Sonne, to ſave the world, as ſoone as it was loſt, and to reſtore man, as yet by an actuall ſentence of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, uncondemned. Theſe choice particulars are in this text: all which with brevity I will orderly and plainly point at. I muſt begin well, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with God himſelfe <hi>(l).</hi> God is in this place in this particle.<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Ego cum pondere pronuntiandum,</hi> ſaith a Father. But if any not ſatiſfied with this Soleciſme ſhould aske this Queſtion, what is his name, and his ſonnes name; Let him know,<note place="margin">Prov. 30.4.</note> 
               <hi>Deus eſt nomen ſuum, &amp; nomen ſuum ipſe eſt,</hi> God is his name, and his name is himſelfe: and if we will be wiſe to ſobriety, let us not be ſo curious to know what he is in himſelfe, as carefull to obſerve what he is to us: Our Creatour in the firſt chapter, our Redeemer in this verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J will]</hi> the will of God is the firſt fountaine, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne cauſe of all things; <hi>He worketh all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the counſell of his owne Will.</hi> He is no idle,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.11.</note> or Idoll God, as ignorants make him, that ſits in the chayre of contemplation, but he is alwaies active and operative, <hi>Curioſus et plenus negotii 'Deus:</hi> A curious, exquiſite, provident God, full of buſineſſe.<note place="margin">Aug.</note> Nor is he houſed above the Moone, as the Peripatetickes would have him, but he taketh care of things below, and that from the higheſt to the loweſt, yet <hi>nec ſuperior in illis, nec infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior in iſtis,</hi> neither ſuperiour in thoſe,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> nor inferiour in theſe; he ſees and forſees all things, from eternity to eternity, as if preſent; he foreknoweth what they ſhal be, he worketh them before they are, decrees them before he workes them, bringes to paſſe what he decrees, and turnes all things he brings to paſſe to his owne peculiar deſigned endes: and this is all <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to the counſell of his will: and in my text
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4303:7"/>
it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the good will and pleaſure of God previſing, purpoſing, providing aforehand, that mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort which he meant to ſhew to his in future genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>I will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But can ſuch bright beames produce ſuch a foggy vapour as enmity? can ſo pure a fountaine ſend forth ſuch troubled ſtreames? Farre be it from the Maker of al things to do that which is unbeſeeming his heavenly moderation and as farre be it from us to conceive ſo of our mercifull Creatour. The rule is true, <hi>Ideo miſit Deus bonam ſeparationem, ut malam rumperet conjunctionem.</hi> God therefore ſent a good ſeparation, that he might diſſolve an evill conjunction. And as for the inference of this enmity,<note place="margin">Zach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7.</note> Grace, Grace unto it: <hi>yea bleſſed be the wombe that bare it, and the paps that gave it ſucke.</hi> This warre is our peace, this ſtrife is our attonement. This enmity betweene Satan and us, is our unity with God, and our amity with the bleſſed Angells: Heere are grapes of thornes, and figs of thiſtles, the ſealed gates of everlaſting life rend open by theſe bruſhes.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.10.</note> This is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the manifold wiſedome of God, that fetcheth about his purpoſes from a farre, and by ſtrange meanes effects his deſignements, workes out his owne ends, and our comforts by contrary inſtruments, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures health by poiſon, takes hony out of a weed, water out of a Rock, oile out of a ſtone, good out of evill, light out of darknes, ſalvation out of enmity. <hi>I will put enmity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing is the parties betwixt whom the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation and contention is, the Serpent and the woman, two companions in evill, confederates in rebellion: now God ſets them at variance.</p>
            <p>It is a rule of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> that ſociety once throughly broken proves deadly, and he gives the reaſon of it, <hi>Quae apud concordes vincula charitatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> 
               <hi>incitamenta irarum apud infenſos ſunt.</hi> Thoſe things which before cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled their friendſhip, in a mutuall, interchangeable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4303:7"/>
are now occaſions of greater deteſtation. The text verefies it: The ſerpent, and the woman were as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as might be, in injuſtice, they tooke ſweet ſowre counſell together, had ſtricken their right hands toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in a wrong fellowſhip, now they are in an uproa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and inteſtine inſurrection, The ſociety that keepes not within the pale of obedience, is nothing elſe but a part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerſhip in conſpiracy, a diſordered Order eaſily bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, Concordia <hi>diſcors,</hi> it begins in ſedition, and ends in contention: and though wicked men ſymbolize in that which is naught, yet God doth Commonly knap in ſunder their ſtaffe of bands, bruiſe the heele or breake the head of their combination. And though there be a day when <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> be made friends,<note place="margin">Luke 23.12.</note> and cleave together in their devices, like the woman and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, againſt the firſt and ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> Yet there ſhall be a time, when they ſhall be ſeparated each from other as farre as the Eaſt from the Weſt, Their affections as farre remote, and diſtant as the Hyena and the dog; the weake ſtrings of their rotten ſociety looſed, and their bowes ſtrongly bent in a mutuall oppoſition. It is juſt with God to ſet them one againſt another, who have ſet themſelves againſt him: and to make revolters from him their Captaine, to mutinize among themſelves. Thus God threatned to ſet the Egyptians againſt the Egyptians; as <hi>Cadmus</hi> his army, bred of ſerpents teeth,<note place="margin">Iſa. 19.2.</note> killed each other. Capitall is this enmity betweene the ſerpent, and the woman: So that you may as ſoone bring the two poles of heaven together, as theſe two to unity. For it is enmity in the abſtract, and ſo it barres the ſubjects of any coalition. Reconciliation may be made betweene enemies, but never where enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelfe is ſetled, as betwixt theſe two: And being thus parted, my diſcourſe muſt likewiſe ſever them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thee]. i.</hi> the Devill: whoſe Creation, or corruption it pleaſed God that <hi>Moſes</hi> his pen ſhould not exactly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4303:8"/>
deſcribe unto us, <hi>et ſecretum ſuum ſibi, nec audemus hic aliquid coniicere, quod ille curauit retinere,</hi> As Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> well,<note place="margin">Bern.</note> upon a better occaſion, Let the Lords ſecrets be with himſelfe: I will not have an eye to ſee, where God hath not a finger to ſet downe. And though I am ignorant of his nature, yet will I ſtrive not to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of his deviſes:<note place="margin">Revel. 20.8.</note> undoubtedly He it is whom the ſpirit of God cals <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The Dragon, the old Serpent, which is the Devill and Satan. A Father briefely deſcribes him and his companions,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> they are <hi>Spiritus nocendi cupidiſſimi, a juſtitia penitus alieni, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbia tumidi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jdem tract. <hi>100</hi> in Ioh.</note> 
               <hi>invidentia lividi, fallacia callidi.</hi> And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place the ſame Father tearms them both <hi>deſertores,</hi> forſakers of God, and <hi>deceptores,</hi> deceivers of us. This is one of the Champions, you may match him with that <hi>Goliah</hi> of the Philiſtines. The other is a weake op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, but comes like <hi>David,</hi> in the Name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The woman</hi>) manneſſe, or ſhe-man according to the originall: mans helper, <hi>dimidium anime,</hi> his better halfe, his yoke-fellow, his ſecond ſelfe. Yet Tranſlators have heere rendered it <hi>Mulier, à Mollitie,</hi> from her niceneſſe, her tenderneſſe of conſtitution, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>genus mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> a Creature that delights in Ornaments. Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> ſayth keenely, ſhe was the Devills engine to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe man.<note place="margin">Tim. 2.14.</note> But Saint <hi>Paul</hi> more mildely, ſhe was of two earthen veſſells the weaker, and deceived in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion: And his concluſion is ſweet, through bearing of children ſhe ſhall be ſaved, for ſhe ſhould at the laſt beare him that ſhould both ſave her, and all true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers.<note place="margin">Prov. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Mulierem fortem quis inveniet,</hi> (ſayth the wiſe man) who can finde a ſtrong, or a vertuous woman! which a Father expounds to be an admiration,<note place="margin">Bern.</note> not a dubitation: For though <hi>Solomon</hi> knew the weakeneſſe of that ſex, yet he looked at the ſtability of Gods promiſe, that the ſame hand ſhould be an inſtrument of woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4303:8"/>
and healing: <hi>Et qui vicerat per foeminam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>vincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur per ipſam.</hi> He that had overcome by the woman, ſhould bee overcome by the woman: though not by the ſame individuall perſon: For divines note that <hi>Eve</hi> imagined her ſelfe to be the mother of the holy ſeed; and therefore when ſhe bare <hi>Cain,</hi> ſhe ſayd,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 4 1.</note> 
               <hi>acquiſivi virum a Iehovah,</hi> I have gotten a man of the Lord: Others more punctually making <hi>(eth)</hi> a ſigne of the accuſative caſe, and not onely ſo,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 4.2.</note> but an emphaticall demonſtrative equivalent to the Greeke Article (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) render it, <hi>Acquiſivi virum, Iehovah, I have gotten that man that is the Lord:</hi> but ſeeing her expectation fruſtrate, ſhe names her next ſonne <hi>Abel,</hi> vanity, to ſhew how vaine her opinion was. For it was not <hi>Eve,</hi> but that handmaid which the Lord had appointed.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the two combatants,<note place="margin">Numb. 22.</note> that ſtand in my Text, like the Angell in <hi>Balaams</hi> way, with their ſwordes in their hands drawne one againſt the other: the perſons whom God ſets at variance: yet neither is this their enmity perſonall, bounded to themſelves, or limited to their proprietaries, but diffuſing it ſelfe through the veines of their ſeed, and like a Gangren, running over the whole body of their poſterity, thy ſeed and her ſeed. Immortall is the hatred and diſſenſion of mortall men, and enmity runnes in a continuall line. The malice kindled among Anceſtors is cheriſhed by ſucceeding progeny: <hi>Nati natorum, et qui naſcentur ab illis:</hi> Children and childrens children will adde fuell to it, and poſſeſſe the inflamed bloud of their parents. To have <hi>Ionathan</hi> Sauls ſonne to love <hi>David</hi> Sauls re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted enemy, is as great a wonder, as to have <hi>Saul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe among the prophets: following generations com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly tread the ſteps of the former:<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> but eſpecially end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe are thoſe quarrells <hi>ubi inimicitiae divina authoritate firmantur.</hi> As in the text, betweene the ſerpent and the woman and their ſeeds.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4303:9"/>
               <hi>Thy ſeed]</hi> Whoſe? The Divels! Surely, we may ſay, as the Diſciples in another caſe, <hi>This is a hard ſaying:</hi> or we may beg with them, <hi>Maſter, teach us theſe things:</hi> there wants ſome <hi>Oedipus</hi> of holy writ to diſſolve this doubt.</p>
            <p>It hath beene the fond opinion of ſome, that Devills are corporeall and have ſeminall propagation. <hi>Pſellus</hi> ſet it a foote, <hi>Cardanus</hi> maintained and confirmed it; and <hi>Scaliger</hi> juſtly confutes it.<note place="margin">Math. 9.34.</note> Probable it is, that there is a chiefe of thoſe wicked ſpirits, ſtiled the <hi>Prince of Divels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2.</note> and <hi>the Prince of the power of the Aire;</hi> and pointed at before in the Text, in that ſingle terme, <hi>thee:</hi> And many others there are, it not ſeduced by him (as <hi>Aquinas</hi> thinkes) yet ſubjected to him, or at leaſt ſharers with him both of his ſinne and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Math 25.</note> called his Angels, and in my text, <hi>his ſeed.</hi> There are alſo others which are of the Serpents ſeed; we ſhall not need rake hell to finde them, they are not of the nature of ſpirits, but cloathed with fleſh and blood: As <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Cataline, Vivunt &amp; in Senatum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niunt,</hi> They live and daily converſe amongſt us. Chriſt cals <hi>Iudas</hi> a divell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.70. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44. <hi>Marlorat. in locum. Aug. in Ioh. tract.</hi> 42.</note> tels the Phariſees, <hi>Ye are of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Divell: Non quoad ſubſtantiae traducem, ſed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae corruptelam,</hi> not in regard of the traduction of their ſubſtance, but the corruption of their nature: <hi>non naſcendo,</hi> as the Manichees held; but, <hi>imitando,</hi> by imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating his curſed workes. Theſe two waies they are the divels ſeed, by corruption of their nature, by imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the divels workes. Such are thoſe, <hi>qui conantur deſtruere fidem,</hi> that endeavour to deſtroy faith, and take that out of the earth, as Tyrants; or <hi>corrumpere fidem,</hi> to corrupt the faith, as Heretickes: When <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> asked <hi>Policarpus, Agnoſcis me?</hi> Doeſt thou know me? His anſwer was, <hi>Agnoſco te primogenitum Satanae:</hi> I know thee to be the divels firſt borne childe: or thoſe that ſeeke <hi>diſrumpere charitatem,</hi> to breake the bond of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4303:9"/>
Chriſtian charity, as Schiſmatiques, and in generall, all carnall unregenerate men, that either truely know not Chriſt, or in the whole courſe of their lives deny him, are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, of that evill one, the Divell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Her ſeed</hi>] The womans ſeed muſt be conceived to be Chriſt and Chriſtians. Chriſt in the firſt place. He was the womans ſeed, of her loynes, of her bowels, bone of her bone, and fleſh of her fleſh;<note place="margin">Euſebius Emiſſenus.</note> he tooke from her a true reall ſubſtantiall body, <hi>Sanguinem quem pro matre obtulit, antea de ſanguine matris accepit:</hi> Contrary to that of the Marcionites and Manichees; the one drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of an imaginary body of his, onely in ſhew, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance and apparition, <hi>corpus Phantaſticum,</hi> the other of a bare heavenly body, which hee brought with him from heaven, and with which hee paſſed through her body, as water through a Conduit-pipe, without any aſſumption of her nature. In my text he was the ſeed of the woman, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.3. Iohn 1.14. Galat. 4.4. Ierem. 31.22.</note> he was made fleſh, made of a woman, (though not by the uſuall courſe of nature.) The Lord ſhall create a new thing in the earth, a woman ſhall compaſſe a man. <hi>Foemina circundans virum eſt virgo concipiens Deum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. Hom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>A Virgin ſhall conceive, and beare God incarnate.</hi> But how a mother, and yet a Virgin? wonder we may, yet we cannot but believe, when the holy Ghoſt ſupplies the place of a parent, <hi>Non goneratione, ſed juſſione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictione,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not by carnall effuſion of ſeminall humour: but by manufacture, or handyworke. I may conclude with Saint <hi>Ambroſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ.</note> 
               <hi>Multa in Chriſto invenies ſecundum naturam, &amp; ultra na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam.</hi> It was naturall that he ſhould be the ſeed of the woman, above nature, that it could be without the ſeed of man. And this is the complement of all humane generations: <hi>Adam</hi> was neither of man, nor woman, but ſlime. <hi>Eve</hi> of a man, without a woman; all wee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4303:10"/>
of man and woman: Chriſt of a woman, without a man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Her ſeed,]. i.</hi> Chriſtians in the ſecond place, which are not ſo properly the womans ſeed, as her ſeeds ſeed, borne not of fleſh and blood,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.13. 1 Pet. 1.23. Pſalm. 22.30.</note> nor of the will of man, but of the Will of God, the Word of God, the ſeed that ſerve God, and are accounted to him for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; not that naturall ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of which God ſaid to him that his ſeed ſhould be <hi>as the duſt of the earth, Geneſ.</hi> 13.16. But that ſpirituall ſeed which ſhould be <hi>as the Starres of Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 15.5</note>
            </p>
            <p>So then his meaning is, that betwixt Chriſt and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers on him, and the Devill, and his adherents in hell, on earth, there is a perpetuall enmity.</p>
            <p>Chriſts enemy the Divell was in his Cradle, on the Croſſe, an enemy at the temptation, in his preaching, in his miracles, and in that whole worke of mans redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>An enemy to Chriſtians he is and ever will be: He makes warre with the remnant of her ſeed which keepe the Commandements of God and have the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">Apoc. 12.17.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 13.</note> He perſecutes thoſe that dwell in heaven, thoſe that live here with erect converſations, lifted up unto the Author and ſiniſher of their faith. It is not thus with the wicked, they feele not the forces of his enmity, <hi>Pax, Pax,</hi> all that they poſſeſſe is in peace, while Satan peaceably poſſeſſeth them: they make a covenant with hell, are at an agreement with death, and ſticke not to ſay,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> as the great Whore, <hi>I ſit as a Queene, and ſhall never be removed.</hi> No man hunts for tamed Fowles, but wild and eſtranged, theſe are his already, it is in vaine to ſeeke their further Captivation. But he lookes with the aſpect of a Baſiliske upon the life of a righteous man. A Saints ſoule is a pearle in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned eye, true believing Chriſtians are the maliced parties, whom hee and his doe proſecute with deadly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4303:10"/>
hatred. <hi>In ſanctificatis nobis maxime diaboli tentamenta graſſantur, quia magis exoptata eſt ei victoria de ſanctis.</hi> Sanctified men are the marke of his temptation, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them he doth principally deſire a victory: As there is joy in heaven over one ſinner that repenteth; ſo is there joy in hell over one righteous man that fals into ſinne, and the ſnares of the Devill, more then over many that are his bond-ſlaves.<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>Adhoc praelium accinge te Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiane.</hi> Buckle thy ſelfe, O Chriſtian to encounter this enemy of thy Maſter, and of thy ſelfe, that hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done thy parents, and ſeekes to deſtroy thee likewiſe, <hi>et pro affectu, pro charitate, pro ipſa denique naturâ,</hi> for affection, for Charity, even for natures ſake, revenge on him theſe injuries, and let him never triumph, and ſet up his banners for tokens in the ruines of them, and thee.</p>
            <p>We muſt all know, that we have ſuch an enemy, that <hi>Viet</hi> armis labours for, and delights in our deſtruction. <hi>Mortalium Calamitates epul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>monum,</hi> our miſeries are his banquetting diſhes, <hi>et ſolatium perditionis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Syneſius.</note> as <hi>Lactantius</hi> thinkes,<note place="margin">Lactant.</note> the onely comfort he hath to bring us into the ſame perdition with himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And that we may more ſeriouſly conſider our dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in regard of him, we may diſcover him to be a powerfull, a Politique, and a malicious enemy, And theſe three concurring in him, the danger is ſo much the greater, power to doe, ſkill to direct and manage, and an inward principle of malice to ſet both braine and hand on worke muſt needs be noxious.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Powerfull he is, of great ſtrength,<note place="margin">Luke 11.</note> and therefore called a ſtrong armed man, he is ſaid to have ten hornes, to denote his great puiſſance, to puſh at the ſervants of God, and caſt them downe. He is <hi>Leo in cubili,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in quo &amp; vis &amp; Dolus,</hi> A Lyon in his denne, in whom there is both ſtrength and deceit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Politique. <hi>Aſtus pollentior armis:</hi> Cunning and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4303:11"/>
skill to manage a battell is of as great conſequence as force, and power; the devill is not wanting in this kinde, he hath his plots and ſtratagems of warre, <hi>Mille nocendi artes.</hi> No <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> comparable to him for deceit, he can tranſforme himſelfe into an Angell of light: No <hi>Proteus</hi> can equall his variableneſſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.</note> and cunning unconſtancy; He is ſaid to have ſeaven heades, now ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is a number of perfection; he is then Maſter of his trade for ſleights and ſubtilties: And this hee hath partly from his knowledge, partly from his experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>His knowledge, either naturall, for he reteines a great part of that he once had, and is deeply acquainted with the Myſteries of ſecond cauſes; or acquired by an eaſie, and infallible way of ſpeculation, not by a tedious ſearching of cauſes by their effects: proceeding <hi>à notis ad ignotiora,</hi> as we doe. Partly from his experience, he is acquainted with all ages and paſſages paſt, and keepes a ſure Regiſter of them. <hi>Seris venit uſus ab annis:</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience comes from old age. He is, and needes muſt be experienced, that is as ancient as the world it ſelfe; therefore he is called that old ſerpent. But theſe two would not diſadvantage us if there was not <hi>nocendi ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> a minde to doe us miſchiefe, but ſuch there is in him: he is</p>
            <p n="3">3. A malitious enmity. Saint <hi>Baſill</hi> writes of the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard, that he beares ſuch a naturall hatred to man, that if he doe but ſee his picture, he is ready to flye upon it, and teare it in peeces: ſuch a ſpirituall hatred hath the Devill to mans ſoule, <hi>Hoc continuum ſtadium ejus, hoc unicum deſiderium, ut animas devoret.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ſol. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> This is his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall ſtudy, his dayly deſire, to devome ſoules.</p>
            <p>Make we uſe then of this briefe diſcovery of our enemy.</p>
            <p>Let his power teach us to give our ſelves unto prayer, that is a Chriſtians beſt offenſive weapon.<note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>Gravis equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4303:11"/>
nobis inimici tentatio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de civ. Dei. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed longe gravior illi noſtra oratio.</hi> Prayer is <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbarde Chriſtianorum</hi> (as <hi>Luther</hi> cals it) and as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> fought with <hi>Eugenius</hi> the tyrant, <hi>Magis orando quàm f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riendo;</hi> ſo muſt wee with this enemy of ours; for when we pray to heaven, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven fights for us, and hee that hath God to his friend needs feare no enemy. And our beſt defenſive, it will be as a ſhield and buckler to ward off all blowes, yea an Armour of proofe againſt all aſſaults. As Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> to his hearers, <hi>Rogo vos fratres, ut ſemper ad manum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beatis tutiſſimum orationes refugium.</hi> But withall,<note place="margin">Bern. ſer. <hi>5.</hi> Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ag.</note> let us remember, that our prayer be not light frozen or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functory, for then it will have no force to offend our enemy, or power to defend our ſelves, but ſuch ſtrong cries as our Saviour is ſaid to ſend up in the daies of his fleſh, to reſiſt our ſtrong adverſary, that his potency may be overcome by that kinde of omnipotency of prayer.</p>
            <p>Let his policy teach us vigilancy, to lie alwaies <hi>in excubiis</hi> in watch and ward, to reſiſt our adverſary, to ſecure our ſelves. <hi>Magna &amp; neceſſaria vigilantia eſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug Euch. ad Lam. c. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> We have need of a great deale of watchfulneſſe, to be carefull to prevent him, who is ſo watchfull to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent us. Why are we then ſo ſecure, O Chriſtians! doe we ſo little prize our owne ſafety, or ſuſpect our enemy? <hi>Sic notus</hi> Ulyſſes: <hi>vigilat hoſtis, dormis tu?</hi> Therefore,<note place="margin">Aug.</note>
               <hi>Ariſe Sampſon, the Philiſtins be upon thee.</hi> Awake O Chriſtian the Philiſtins of hell be upon thee.</p>
            <p>His malice will teach us wiſedome, to be wiſe as ſerpents to reſiſt that old ſerpent the divell: let us be ſure to preſerve our head Chriſt by faith, not to put off our skinne, our armour, but in a certaine ſecurity, that which is in heaven, and for the preſent to have ever about us that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 9. Laſtly to carry about us our ſting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Word of God, <hi>Scriptum eſt,</hi> which is,<note place="margin">Origen. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er.</note> 
               <hi>ſupra omnia tormentorum genera,</hi> above all kinde of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4303:12"/>
torments to the Devill, the onely way to deſtroy him.</p>
            <p>And as we have, ſo we ever ſhall have ſuch an one, an implacable, an irreconcileable adverſary, <hi>Habemus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium nullo unquam foedere dirimendum.</hi> We have a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference that ſhall never be compoſed, a warre that no truce ſhall ever take up. Therefore let us not thinke of a league or dreame of any conditions of peace, <hi>Male cum hoſte conjungitur a quo divinâ ſententiâ ſeparatur.</hi> It is ill combining our ſelves with him from whom Gods commandement doth ſeparate us. There muſt be no harmony where the chiefe muſitian will have a jarre: this diſcord pleaſeth God: And the Lord of hoaſtes hath inrolled us in his Muſter booke to be his ſouldiers. Let us ſight manfully theſe battells. <hi>Et, bella geri pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat magnos habitura triumphos.</hi> Let us wage theſe wars, which will have both a certaine victory, and a glorious triumph.</p>
            <p>An enmity there is we ſee, betweene Chriſtians, and the ſerpent with his infernall ſeed. Nor is it otherwiſe with his terreſtriall: <hi>they are of their father the Devill, and his workes they will doe.</hi> Hitherto tend the practiſes of Tyrants,<note place="margin">Bern. de pugna ſpirit. ſer. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Heretiques, and Schiſmatiques, to oppoſe Chriſt and Chriſtians. <hi>Inter Babylonem, et Ieruſalem nulla pax, ſed guerra continua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 25.</note>So that I may ſay of my text, as God did of <hi>Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca's</hi> wombe: two ſeverall nations are in it, and two manner of people to be divided out of the loines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Chriſtians, and unbeleevers; ſheepe, and goates; the Children of promiſe, and the children of the fleſh; the children of God, and the children of the Devill; betwixt whom there will ever be a diviſion, ſeparation, a partition wall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a great gulfe of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. I finde the <hi>Geneſis</hi> of this enmity heere in my text, the <hi>Exodus</hi> thereof I know not where, nor when to finde: From the beginning it was thus, now is, <hi>et ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candeſcit
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4303:12"/>
eundo,</hi> it gets ſtrength the further it goes: And when an Angell from heaven hath ſworne by him that liveth for ever, there ſhall be no more time; then, and not till then, there ſhall be no more enmity. I alleadge no other reaſon then that of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.</note> 
               <hi>what communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath light with Darkeneſſe</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For my part, I will not blow the Coales of diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there are too many <hi>Phaetons</hi> that ſet the world in a combuſtion: <hi>Et utinam abſcindantur,</hi> ſay I, with the Apoſtle, I would they were even cut off that are troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of peace.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> We cannot but ſee and condole the enmity, that is betweene the womans proper ſeed, and how her children ſtruggle within her to her great paine and travaile; heere is not onely <hi>Jſmael's</hi> hand, but <hi>Iſaac's</hi> hand againſt <hi>Iſaac,</hi> one Chriſtian againſt another, as though we meant of purpoſe to verifie that which our Saviour ſpake <hi>ex hypotheſi: I came not to ſend peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10.35.</note>
               <hi>but a ſword, to ſet a man at variance againſt his father, and the Daughter againſt her mother.</hi> Or that other: <hi>there ſhall be five in one houſe divided; three againſt two,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12.52.</note> 
               <hi>and two againſt three.</hi> The Poet complaines <hi>Serpentum concordia major, quàm hominum interſe. Inven.</hi> There is more agreement of Serpents among themſelves, then of men; nay betwixt Devills, then Chriſtians:<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Legiones Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monum in uno homine convenerunt, et duo homines in unâ domo vix conveniunt.</hi> A Legion of Devills could agree together in one man, and two Chriſtians can ſcarce agree in one houſe. Surely prodigious is our inteſtine enmity; And though God did graciouſly in my text make it the Churches reſtitution, yet we ſeeke to make it her ruine. It is obſerved, that when ſheepe fall a but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one againſt another, a ſtorme followes not long after: when the ſheepe of Chriſt are ſo malignant one to another, it is a fearefull preſage of an enſuing ſtorme. They ſay of Bees, when they ſtirre and ſtrive among themſelves, it is a ſigne their King is about to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4303:13"/>
remove and leave the hive. When we make ſuch ſtirres, tumults, and ſchiſmes in Religion, it may be feared, God is going to remove from us. But let us all labour to continue his preſence ſtill among us, that he may ſtill take delight to walke in the middeſt of the ſeaven Golden Candeleſtickes. O pray for, and practiſe the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that he who makes men to be of one mind in an houſe would make us to be of one heart and of one ſoule together in a bleſſed communion of Saints, which may never be diſſevered; and let us all endeavour to <hi>keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Leave we then this enmity, and follow the line of my text, and it will bring us to the Prince of peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee) Fauſtus</hi> the Manichee puts a rub in my way, in ſaying the old Teſtament had nothing in it prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall concerning Chriſt: but I will eaſily ſtep over it; for who was <hi>Iacobs Shiloh, I ſaiahs Immanuel, Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Branch, and this <hi>ſemen mulieris</hi> in the text, but Chriſt? And the vulgar tranſlation ſeemes to ſtop my courſe, <hi>ipſa</hi> ſhe ſhall; ſo it reades the word. And the Papiſts commonly, either to dignifie the Mother above the Sonne, that ſhe, not he, ſhould breake the ſerpents head, as moſt of their wooden Prieſtes, and many of their brazen faced Ieſuites: or by the Sonne, that ſhe by him ſhould breake the Serpents head, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> with more modeſty, but <hi>Ribera</hi> with a few others, with more honeſty, doe acknowledge it wholly to belong to Chriſt, according to the Originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: he, and he alone could breake the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head, without any further Damage then a bruiſed heele.</p>
            <p>The power of Chriſt is deſcribed both by the effect which it produceth, and the object it worketh upon.</p>
            <p>The Object is the head, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or the higheſt part of the body, and moſt ſoveraigne for the direction
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4303:13"/>
of it, <hi>caput,</hi> becauſe the ſenſes doe <hi>capere initium,</hi> take their beginning from thence. The effect is breaking, the word ſignifies not onely to weare and waſt by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, but to breake as a ſhip is broken in a tempeſt, it is ſo uſed <hi>Iob</hi> 9.17. (And further there is an Ellipſis of the particle. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>)</p>
            <p>Both theſe imply the totall and finall victory of Chriſt. The part is dangerous, the head: the wound is deadly, and ſhall never be healed, <hi>he ſhall breake thy head.</hi> Thus the prophet;<note place="margin">Iſa. 17.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord ſhall pierce Leviathan that crooked ſerpent:</hi> and our Saviour himſelfe,<note place="margin">Luke 10.18.</note> 
               <hi>I beheld Satan as lightning fall from heaven:</hi> and that beloved Diſciple, <hi>for this purpoſe the Sonne of God was manifeſted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>that he might deſtroy the workes of the Devill.</hi> Theſe workes were of Adoration, of conſultation and of temptation.</p>
            <p>Of Adoration: For before Chriſts incarnation he did tyrannize over the world, and his kingdome was eſtabliſht, he was generally then adored and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, as he is now by <hi>Indians in Dei imitationem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſebius.</note> as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> obſerves, after the manner of God; nay humane fleſh was not too precious to doe ſacrifice to him: even among Gods people their tender infants muſt not be ſpared to paſſe through the fire unto <hi>Moloch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 32.35.</note> which ſome thinke to be <hi>Mercury,</hi> others <hi>Saturne,</hi> others <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> the King of the Gods, (<hi>Melech,</hi> and by corruption <hi>Moloch</hi>) which Gods of the Nations were truely De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills. And that addition which Saint <hi>Steven</hi> ſets downe, gives a liberty of conjecture that it was <hi>Deus tutelaris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 7.43.</note> the tutelary God of the Ammonites, to him was this bloudy ſacrifice powred out: but when the fulneſſe of the time was come, theſe bloudy ſacrifices were broken off, Chriſt aboliſhed this tyranny, and tooke the ſcepter into his owne hand, to governe his people by righteous lawes, and commandements, which are not grievous, till they come to reigne with himſelfe in his heavenly Kingdome,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:4303:14"/>2. Conſultation. His Oracles were then the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule of counſell and advice, both for publike and private actions, till Chriſt came; who having the words of eternall life, brought grace and truth into the world: And then all his Oracles ceaſed; as it is recorded of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> who enquiring at the Oracle at <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos</hi> who ſhould ſucceed him in the Empire, had this for an anſwer,
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Peucerus.</note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
               <hi>An Hebrew Child, King of the Gods, hath commanded me to leave this Houſe, and to returne to Hell, therefore hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth forſake our Altars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Temptation: whereby he corrupted the hearts, and lives of men: The vigour of this is taken away by Chriſt, ſo that his ſollicitations are not ſo prevalent as they were before,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> becauſe Chriſt was in all points tempted like as we are, yet without ſinne, and ſo is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In ſumme: venit, vidit, vicit,</hi> he came from heaven, he ſaw the earth, he overcame the Devill: he ſpoyled Principalities and Powers,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.15. Hebr. 2.14. Pſal. 68.18.</note> 
               <hi>He hath deſtroyed death, and him that had the Power of death, that it the Devill. When he aſcended on high, he led captivitie captive;</hi> that is, the captivity of the Devill, as <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> expounds it: then was my text fully accompliſhed, and the ſerpents head was broken.</p>
            <p>Now if we aske the ground of Chriſts quarrell with the ſerpent, and the occaſion of this victory: We muſt know the cauſe was ours, the ſerpent had broken our head firſt, therefore Chriſt undertooke for us, and brake the ſerpents head: The conqueſt is ours, communicated to us now, and to be conſummate when we come to heaven. The comfort is ours, that our Captaine hath conquered our enemy, and we need not feare to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with a broken ſtaffe <hi>a Debilitated opponent;</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:4303:14"/>
And the thankfulneſſe muſt be ours, to ſing every day ſome ſong of thankeſgiving unto him that hath taken us out of the fanges, and throat of deſtruction.<note place="margin">Luke 1.75</note> And this muſt be remembred, <hi>that we being delivered out of the hands of our enemies, muſt ſerve him without feare, in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe before him, all the daies of our life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I come to the laſt part of my text, which is like the ſting in the tayle of the Scorpion, <hi>Thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The hurt our Saviour received, did principally light on him on the Croſſe; touching which, if ſence be Iudge, more then his heele was bruiſed; and his heele more then bruiſed: but faith will teſtifie, that but his heele was but bruiſed: For he ſaw no corruption, he delivered himſelfe from death; he revived his dead aſhes, built againe his deſtroyed Temple within three dayes, and on the fourtieth after, caryed it up with him into heaven, and crowned it with immortality. So that, the phraſe is elegant, being a reſemblance of the humane nature of Chriſt, of a paſſible quality and condition: and an intimation of his divine, ſuſtaining his weake manhood to endure thoſe ſufferings, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt thoſe bitter pilles, and to make them medicinall to himſelfe, and his.<note place="margin">Greg. Ni</note> 
               <hi>Naturae noſtrae integumento caelata fuit divinitas, ut inſtar Piſcium, cum eſcâ carnis ſimul attraheretur hamus divinitatis.</hi> Chriſt like a skillfull fiſher, did cover and hide his Godhead with the worme of his humane nature: now the Devill thinking to ſwallow the worme of his humanity, <hi>captus eſt hamo divinitatis,</hi> was caught with the hooke of his divinity: and ſo in bruiſing Chriſts heele, his owne head was broken. Or like a cunning wraſtler, Chriſt did ſet out the heele of his humanity for his adverſary to ſtrike at, and with the hand of his divinity caſt him downe, yea broke his head.</p>
            <p>Nor is this applyed onely to that one paſſion of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4303:15"/>
Chriſt, but extended to all his ſufferings, which ſhall be for ever accompliſhed in his militant members. For he is the head, the Church is his body, beleevers the ſeverall parts of it: he muſt needs then be ſenſible of of their ſufferings, and their damages and hurts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to him.<note place="margin">Acts 9.4. <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? non ait, quid ſanctos meos, quid ſervos meos, ſed quid me perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queris? hoc eſt, membra mea: Caput pro membris clamabat, et membra in ſe caput tranſſigurabat.</hi> He ſaith not, why perſecuteſt thou my Saints, my ſervants; but me, my members? The head cryed for the members, and did transfigure them as it were into it ſelfe. So that his heele may be ſaid to be bruiſed, when his children are tempted by ſatan, or afflicted by his malicious ſeed.</p>
            <p>Two things naturally ariſe from hence.</p>
            <list>
               <item>A tolleration of the Serpents malice.</item>
               <item>A limitation of his might.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt, God doth ſuffer the Serpent to exerciſe his malice on the members of Chriſt here below, to bruiſe their heeles, and that either for their tryall, as to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.31. 2 Cor. 12.</note> or for their humiliation, as to Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> or for ſome other end, which himſelfe beſt knoweth. I am ſure, all things ſhall worke together for their good;<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>etiam peccata,</hi> even their ſinnes, either <hi>ad poeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi> or, <hi>ad cautelam;</hi> to make them repent of ſinne paſt, or take heed of ſinne for the future: and the brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their heeles ſhall be the ſaving of their ſoules: yet bruiſed they muſt be. <hi>Conteritur quidem ſerpentis caput,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>ſed facile eſt experiri calcaneo inſidiantem.</hi> Chriſt hath taken us out of the divels clawes, notwithſtanding wee are not yet out of the reach of his chaine: <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dico adhuc tempore ſinitur malignari.</hi> A little while he is ſuffered to bruiſe our heele,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.20.</note> but the God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under our feet ſhortly.</p>
            <p>And as God ſuffers the divell himſelfe to tempt them, ſo doth he his Impes to afflict them here; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4303:15"/>
               <hi>Abel</hi> is ſlaine by curſed <hi>Cain; Ioſeph</hi> ſold by his wicked brethren, the Children of Iſrael in bondage under <hi>Pharaoh, Iohn Baptiſt</hi> beheaded for a daunce,<note place="margin">Revel. 14.15.</note> here then is the patience of the Saints.</p>
            <p>Let us then be contented to have our heeles bruiſed: It is happineſſe enough to get the bleſſing, though with <hi>Iacob</hi> we be ſent halting to our graves. Therefore let every one reſolve with himſelfe, <hi>Totum licet ſaeculum pereat, nihil moror, dum patientiam lucrifaciam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul.</note> Let the whole world periſh; I care not, ſo I may gaine patience.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond. God doth not ſuffer the Devill to wreake his malice, and to powre out the full viols of his ſpight on them, but ſets him his boundes which he cannot paſſe: he muſt but bruiſe their heele: his malice is limited, his power is reſtreined; he can goe no further then the permitting hand of heaven will give him leave:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> Job 1. Job 2. Math. 8.</note>
               <hi>Ne oviculam unam;</hi> hee could not touch one of <hi>Iobs</hi> ſheepe, till he had his commiſſion; nor his body till it was renewed: nor enter into the heard of Swine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſts ſufferance, muchleſſe can hee goe beyond his licence in touching the ſoules of the Elect by temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. I confeſſe his malice is boundleſſe, endleſſe, inexorable, as the grave or hell, never ſatisfied: But God puts his hooke in his noſtrils, bounds him with a <hi>huc uſque,</hi> hither ſhalt thou goe, and no further; here ſhalt thou ſtay the proud waves of thy malice, thou ſhalt but bruiſe his heele. As <hi>Achilles</hi> being dipt in the Stygian lake, had his body ſo impenetrable, that no part of it could be endangered but his heele: ſo the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full being waſhed in the precious blood of Chriſt, have ſuch a ſtrong munition for their ſoules, that their vitall parts cannot be endamaged; their heeles may be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, but their head and heart are ſure enough: Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſweetly to this purpoſe; <hi>Eſt quidem Leo rugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, ſed gratias ago Leoni de tribu Inda, rugire iſte poteſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern in Pſal. qui habitat. ſer. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4303:16"/>
               <hi>ferire non poteſt.</hi> The Devill is a roaring Lyon, but I give thanks to him that is the Lyon of the tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> he may roare, but he cannot devoure. And Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Temp. ſer. <hi>197.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Latrare poteſt, ſollicitare poteſt, ſed mordere non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt niſi volentem,</hi> He may ſollicite us to ſinne, he may barke at us, but he cannot bite us, unleſſe we give him leave to faſten. So much doe wee owe to our bleſſed Saviour.</p>
            <p>Finally, as God ſhortens the divels hornes; ſo hee doth his hands, his inſtruments, that they can goe no further to the dammage of his, then he permits them: And <hi>God is faithfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>who will not ſuffer his to be tempted above that they are able.</hi> And when hee hath chaſtened them enough, he will throw the rod into the fire: here is the comfort of the Saints; that God will hedge about his Church with his providence, and encloſe it in a maze of his mercies, that the gates of hell ſhall never be able to prevaile againſt it.</p>
            <p>Therefore, be comforted ye weake hands, be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ye feeble knees, cheere up ye drooping ſpirits; doubtleſſe we have a ſtrong City:<note place="margin">Iſaiah 26.1.</note> Salvation will God appoint for walls and bulwarkes. And let this be our conſolation, that Chriſt hath overcome the world, and greater is he that is with us, then he that is with the world. Now to him that is the greateſt of all, to God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the Holy Ghoſt, be given all due honour, praiſe, ſervice, and thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, now, and for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4303:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
